Guide to the Ellwood Patterson Cubberley Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ellwood Patterson Cubberley papers
1886-1965
SC0212
Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson, 1868-1941
3.25 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Most of the material in the Cubberley Papers were at one time part of another miscellaneous collection. In 1979 some files from the Cubberley Library were sent to the University Archives. At that time these files were combined with those papers in the miscellaneous collection and were made into an independent collection. The collection was partially processed and a preliminary listing was made. This entire collection was re-processed in 1983. Many of the diplomas and awards are oversize, and for this reason they are kept in the print collection (P205).
Information about Access
None.
Associated Materials
Champion in Elocution, Antioch Public Schools, 1878
Indiana University: Bachelor of Arts, in Physics, 1891(signed by Indiana president, David Starr Jordan, June 1891)
Columbia University, Teachers College: Masters Diploma in Education, 1902
Columbia University: Masters in art, 1902
Columbia University, Teachers College: Doctors Diploma in Education, 1905
Columbia University: Doctor of Philosophy, 1905
Columbia University: Butler Silver Medal for Competence in Educational Theory, 1915
Panama-Pacific International Exposition: commemorative medal of bronze for distinguished service, 1915
Cubberley Anniversary Fund, 1923
Pi Gamma Mu: membership, 1926
National Education Association of the United States: Active member for life, 1933
National Education Association of the United States: Honorary life member, 1933
Letter, William G. Carr to Jesse B. Sears, 13 December 1954re: Cubberley's membership
Columbia University: The University Medal, 1933
Indiana University: Doctor of Laws (honorary), 1934
State University of Iowa: Doctor of Laws (honorary), 19342 copies (dummy and original)
BIOGRAPHY
Ellwood Patterson Cubberley was born in Andrews, Indiana June 8, 1868. In 1891 Cubberley received an A.B. from Indiana University, where he met David Starr Jordan, who was president of the university. Cubberley received an M.A. in 1902 and a Ph.D. in 1905, both from Columbia University. On June 15, 1892 Cubberley and Helen Van Uxem, a student he had met at the University of Indiana, were married.
Between 1891 and 1893 Cubberley served as an instructor in physical sciences at Vincennes University in Indiana. He then became president of Vincennes and served from 1893 to 1896. While President, Cubberley brought the university out of debt and established it as an accredited junior college.
From Vincennes Cubberley went to California as the superintendent of the San Diego City Schools. Two years later he accepted an offer from David Starr Jordan, who had become the first president of Stanford University, for the position of assistant professor of education. He became full professor in 1906 and became the dean of the School of Education when it was established in 1917. He served as dean until his retirement in 1933. Cubberley is credited with strengthening the department and building it into an influential School of Education.
Throughout his career Cubberley also did much work lecturing and writing, and served as the head of many school district surveys. Cubberley wrote and edited many books, most notably the Riverside Textbooks in Education.
In 1934, with money they had saved and invested throughout the years, the Cubberleys created a trust fund which was used for the building of the new School of Education. It was completed in 1938.
Cubberley died on September 14, 1941. Helen Cubberley died on January 25, 1952. The Cubberleys did not have children.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The collection contains a wide variety of material. This includes correspondence, articles, speeches, clippings, certificates, ephemera, drawings (charts by Cubberley) and other legal and financial documents. This material reflects almost every aspect of Cubberley's life, although the collection is clearly lacking the bulk of Cubberley's office files created while he served as dean of the School of Education.
Access Terms
Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson, 1868-1941; Cubberley, Helen Van Uxem, d. 1952.; Sears, Jesse.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education.; Education, Higher.; Education, Secondary.
Collection Contents
- CORRESPONDENCE
  - General, 1888-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1937-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative files, 1898-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative files, 1912-1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Administrative files, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Administrative files, 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- WRITINGS BY CUBBERLEY
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Essays and Papers, 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Quotations copied by Cubberley, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Articles
    - 1. "Syllabus of School Management," Boston: Ginn and Co., 1901 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 2. "The School Situation in San Francisco," Educational Review, Apr-01
    - 3. "Address of the Day" (re public schools), The Normal Outlook, Vol. IV, no. 4, 5-Dec-13
    - 4. "Syllabus Outline on Courses on State School Administration," Stanford University Press, 1914
    - 5. "Help Backward School Children," Stanford Alumnus, Apr-14
    - 6. "Fundamental Problems in Educational Administration," Educational Administration and Supervision, Jan-15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 7. "A Declaration of the Principles of the National Educational Association," School and Society, Vol. II, no. 37, 11-Sep-15
    - 8. "Desirable Reorganizations in American Education," School and Society, Vol. II, no. 38, 18-Sep-15
    - 9. "Supplemental Report on the Organization of School District Number One in the City and County of Denver," The School Survey Committee, Denver, Colorado, 1916
    - 10. "Some Recent Developments in Secondary Education in California," Education, (Boston University College of Liberal Arts)., Oct-16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 11. "Report of the Special Legislative Committee on Education," (Senate Concurrent Resolution no. 21, 43rd Session of the Legislature of California, 1920
    - 12. "The College of Education and the Superintendent of Schools," School and Society, Vol. XVII, no. 438.
    - 13. "The American School Program From the Standpoint of the Nation," School and Society, Vol. XVIII, no. 449., 4-Aug-23
    - 14. "Report of the Reviewing Committee on the Reorganization and Housing Program of the San Francisco Schools,", 5-May-24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 15. "A Distinctive American Achievement," Educational Progress, vol. 5, no. 2, Jan-26
    - 16. "The School Textbook Problem," Education Progress, vol. 6, no. 2, Mar-27
    - 17. "Outgrown District School System Impedes Educational Progress," The Nevada Tax Review, no. 1S, May-28
    - 18. "What Should be the Professional Relationship Between Teacher and Principal, Principal and Superintendent, and Teacher and Superintendent' Montana Education, Vol VII, no. 7, Mar-31
    - 19. "Measuring Instruction in History", undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 20. "Plan of Supervision of Rural Schools,", undated
- WRITINGS ABOUT CUBBERLEY
  - Letters of recommendation (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Outline of biography by Jesse Sears. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1891-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cremin, Lawrence. The Wonderful World of Ellwood Patterson Cubberley. New York: Teachers College, Columbia University, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - California Quarterly of Secondary Education, commemorative issue, Apr-33 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1921-1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- SUPERINTENDENT OF SAN DIEGO SCHOOLS
  - Correspondence, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- HONORS AND AWARDS
  - Butler Silver Medal (Columbia University), 1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University Silver Medal for Excellence, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, "Greetings", 1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, Congratulatory letters on 25 years of Service to Stanford University, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Phi Delta Theta, Golden Legion Award, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Resolutions on Cubberley's retirement, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Retirement Dinner, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - list of contributors to the Cubberley Program
    - Signatures of those present at the dinner
  - Retirement Dinner, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - speeches made
  - Retirement Dinner, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - correspondence regarding the preparation of the dinner
  - Retirement Dinner, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - miscellaneous
  - Testimonial Dinner to Helen Van Uxem Cubberley, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Tribute volume, Ellwood P. Cubberley, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Tribute volume, Helen Van Uxem Cubberley, 1939 (Box 4)
- RIVERSIDE TEXTBOOKS IN EDUCATION
  - Correspondence, 1911-1933 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Writings about the series, lists of books (Box 5, Folder 2)
- CUBBERLEY LECTURE FUND
  - Correspondence, notes, 1934-1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- CUBBERLEY LIBRARY FUND
  - Correspondence, notes, 1938-Oct 1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, notes, Nov 1941-1951 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Riverside Textbook royalties (Box 5, Folder 6)
- SCHOOL OF EDUCATION BUILDING
  - Trust Fund--Board of Trustees Correspondence, 1933-1940 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Trust Fund--Board of Trustees, A.F. Manspeaker Correspondence, 1936-Nov 1937 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Trust Fund--Board of Trustees, A.F. Manspeaker Correspondence, Dec 1937-1939 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Trust Fund--Letters in reaction to the Cubberley gift, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Trust Fund--Securities and Financial Statements, 1933-1936 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Trust Fund--Securities and Financial Statements, 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Trust Fund--Securities listings (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Trust Fund--Legal Agreements (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Trust Fund--Notations (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Building Specifications, etc. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous papers--checks, receipts, 1937-1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Names on the facade of the building--description (Box 6, Folder 5)
- ESTATE AND WILL RECORDS
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan-Jul 1942 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1942-1944 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Will of Ellwood P. Cubberley; Will of Helen Van Uxem Cubberley (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Death certificate of Ellwood P. Cubberley, 14-Sep-41 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Frank Van Uxem Trust Fund (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Frank Van Uxem Trust Fund (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous documents (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous documents (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous documents (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - General financial records (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - General financial records, notebooks of accounts, 1909-1941 (Box 7, Folder x)
  - General financial records, cards listing stocks and bonds (Box 8, Folder x)
  - General financial records, cards listing stocks and bonds (Box 9, Folder x)
- GENEALOGY
  - Correspondence, 1907-1936 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1967, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Writings on the Cubberley family (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Cubberley, Helen. Newbold Family Notes, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- MISCELLANEOUS
  - Calling cards, poster, resolution of the Faculty of the School of Education on Cubberley's death (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Resumes, teachers license, registration books for Columbia University (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Charts by Cubberley: (Box 11)
    - Political Parties of the United States, 1889
    - History of Mathematics, 1890
    - Historical Geography, 1891
- RIVERSIDE TEXTBOOKS IN EDUCATION
  - Recordbook of financial data, 1910-1939 (Box 12 (os))
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2002-060
  This accession pertains to a proposed book by Allen and Cubberley, Everyday School Administration.
  - Letters to Cubberley, possibly selected as source material for the book, 1917-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book outline and preface (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Riverside Textbooks in Education, Accession ARCH-2009-219
  - George C. Kyte, How to Supervise (Box 1)
  - John C. Almack, Research and Thesis Writing (Box 1)
  - Harold Benjamin, An Introduction to Human Problems (Box 1)
  - Clarence R. Stone, Supervision of the Elementary School (Box 1)
  - Albert R. Lang, Modern Methods in Written Examination (Box 1)
  - Ernest W. Tiegs & Claude C. Crawford, Statistics for Teachers (Box 1)
  - Lois Coffey Mossman, Principles of Teaching and Learning in the Elementary School (Box 1)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Public School Administration (Box 1)
  - Fowler D. Brooks, The Psychology of Adolescence (Box 1)
  - Walter Robinson Smith, An Introduction to Educational Sociology (Box 1)
  - Walter Robinson Smith, Principles of Educational Sociology (Box 1)
  - Martin J. Stormzand and Jane W. McKee, The Progressive Primary Teacher (Box 1)
  - Claude C. Crawford, The Technique of Study (Box 1)
  - Lawrence Augustus Averill, The Hygiene of Instruction (Box 1)
  - John C. Almack and Albert R. Lang, The Beginning Teacher (Box 1)
  - Reginald Stevens Kimball, Current-Events Instruction (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Keene, The Physical Welfare of the School Child (Box 1)
  - Claude C. Crawford and Lois P. McDonald, Modern Methods in Teaching Geography (Box 1)
  - Lewis M. Terman and John C. Almack, The Hygiene of the School Child (Box 1)
  - William Martin Proctor, Vocations (Box 1)
  - Thomas Cooke McCracken and Helen Etta Lamb, Occupational Information in the Elementary School (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, The Principal and His School (Box 2)
  - Harlan C. Hines, A Guide to Educational Measurements (Box 2)
  - Charles E. Martz and John A. Kinneman, Social Science for Teachers (Box 2)
  - John C. Almack, Education for Citizenship (Box 2)
  - L. A. Pechstein and A. Laura McGregor, Psychology of the Junior High School Pupil (Box 2)
  - Ruby Minor, Principles of Teaching Practically Applied (Box 2)
  - Lawrence Augustus Averill, Elements of Educational Psychology (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, A Brief History of Education (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Rural Life and Education (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Public School Administration (Box 2)
  - Arnold Gesell, The Pre-School Child (Box 2)
  - Walter Scott Monroe, An Introduction to the Theory of Educational Measurements (Box 2)
  - Clarence R. Stone, Silent and Oral Reading (Box 2)
  - Frank W. Thomas, Training for Effective Study (Box 2)
  - Lawrence Augustus Averill, Psychology for Normal Schools (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Readings in the History of Education (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, The History of Education (Box 2)
  - Thomas H. Briggs, The Junior High School (Box 2)
  - Hubert Wilbur Nutt, The Supervision of Instruction (Box 2)
  - N. D. Showalter, A Handbook for Rural School Officers (Box 2)
  - Lewis M. Terman, Condensed Guide for the Stanford Revision of the Binet-Simon Intelligence Tests (Box 2)
  - Lewis M. Terman, The Intelligence of School Children (Box 2)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Public Education in the United States (Box 2)
  - George Earl Freeland, Roxana Morton Adams and Katharine Hedges Hall, Teaching in the Intermediate Grades (Box 3)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, State School Administration (Box 3)
  - Clarence R. Stone, Silent and Oral Reading (Box 3)
  - Aubrey A. Douglass, Secondary Education (Box 3)
  - Jesse B. Sears, Classroom Organization and Control (Box 3)
  - Charles Swain Thomas, The Teaching of English (Box 3)
  - J. E. Wallace Wallin, Clinical and Abnormal Psychology (Box 3)
  - John C. Almack and James F. Bursch, The Administration of Consolidated and Village Schools (Box 3)
  - Ralph S. Newcomb, Modern Methods of Teaching Arithmetic (Box 3)
  - Harl R. Douglass, Modern Methods in High School Teaching (Box 3)
  - Lawrence Augustus Averill, Educational Hygiene (Box 3)
  - Frank N. Freeman, Mental Tests (Box 3)
  - L. A. Pechstein and Frances Jenkins, Psychology of the Kindergarten-Primary Child (Box 3)
  - Frank W. Thomas, Principles and Technique of Teaching (Box 3)
  - J. Crosby Chapman and George S. Counts, Principles of Education (Box 3)
  - J. E. Wallace Wallin, The Education of Handicapped Children (Box 3)
  - Walter Scott Monroe, James Clarence DeVoss and Frederick James Kelly, Educational Tests and Measurements (Box 3)
  - Martin J. Stormzand, Progressive Methods of Teaching (Box 3)
  - J. Harold Williams, Graphic Methods in Education (Box 3)
  - John C. Almack and Albert R. Lang, Problems of the Teaching Profession (Box 3)
  - Jesse B. Sears, The School Survey (Box 3)
  - Harold Rugg, A Primer of Graphics and Statistics (Box 3)
  - Benjamin Floyd Pittenger, An Introduction to Public School Finance (Box 3)
  - A. S. Edwards, The Psychology of Elementary Education (Box 3)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, An Introduction to the Study of Education and to Teaching (Box 3)
  - William Martin Proctor, Educational and Vocational Guidance (Box 3)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Miscellaneous Papers I, 1892-1915 (Box 4)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Miscellaneous Papers II, 1916-1933 (Box 4)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Monroe’s Encyclopedia of Education–Cubberley Articles on School Administration (Box 4)
  - William Martin Proctor, Charles Gilbert Wrenn and Glidden Ross Benefield, Workbook in Vocations (Box 4)
  - William Giles Campbell, A Form Book for Thesis Writing (Box 4)
  - Norma E. Cutts and Nicholas Moseley, Practical School Discipline and Mental Hygiene (Box 4)
  - Roy O. Billett, Fundamentals of Secondary-School Teaching with Emphasis on the Unit Method (Box 4)
  - Herbert G. Espy, The Public Secondary School (Box 4)
  - Lewis M. Terman and Maud A. Merrill, Printed Card Material for Revised Stanford-Binet Tests, Form L (Box 4)
  - Lewis M. Terman and Maud A. Merrill, Printed Card Material for Revised Stanford-Binet Tests, Form M (Box 4)
  - Paul McKee, Language in the Elementary School (Box 4)
  - Ernest W. Tiegs, Tests and Measurements in the Improvement of Learning (Box 4)
  - Frank N. Freeman, Mental Tests (Box 4)
  - Aubrey A. Douglass, Modern Secondary Education (Box 4)
  - Lewis M. Terman and Maud A. Merrill, Directions for Administering Forms L and M (Box 4)
  - Edwin J. Brown, Secondary-School Administration (Box 4)
  - Lewis M. Terman and Maud A. Merrill, Measuring Intelligence (Box 4)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, The History of Education (Box 4)
  - John C. Almack, Modern School Administration (Box 4)
  - Joseph S. Butterweck and J. Conrad Seegers, An Orientation Course in Education (Box 4)
  - Norma V. Scheidemann, The Psychology of Exceptional Children (Box 5)
  - Frank W. Thomas and Albert R. Lang, Principles of Modern Education (Box 5)
  - Nelson L. Bossing, Progressive Methods of Teaching in Secondary Schools (Box 5)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Readings in Public Education in the United States (Box 5)
  - I. L. Kandel, Comparative Education (Box 5)
  - Edwin J. Brown, Everyday Problems in Classroom Management (Box 5)
  - Paul McKee, Reading and Literature in the Elementary School (Box 5)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley and Walter Crosby Eells, An Introduction to the Study of Education (Box 5)
  - Leo J. Brueckner and Ernest O. Melby, Diagnostic and Remedial Teaching (Box 5)
  - Ernest W. Tiegs, Tests and Measurements for Teachers (Box 5)
  - William Clark Trow, Educational Psychology (Box 5)
  - Walter Crosby Eells, The Junior College (Box 5)
  - Elbert K. Fretwell, Extra-Curricular Activities in Secondary Schools (Box 5)
  - Norma V. Scheidemann, The Psychology of Exceptional Children (Box 5)
  - George C. Kyte, Problems in School Supervision (Box 5)
  - Florence M. Baker, The Teaching of French (Box 5)
  - I. L. Kandel, History of Secondary Education (Box 5)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Public Education in the United States (Box 5)
  - Paul McKee, Language in the Elementary School (Box 5)
  - Harl R. Douglass and Charles W. Boardman, Supervision in Secondary Schools (Box 5)
  - Alexander Inglis, Principles of Secondary Education (Box 6)
  - Lee Emerson Bassett, A Handbook of Oral Reading (Box 6)
  - Gilbert H. Trafton, The Teaching of Science in the Elementary School (Box 6)
  - Frank N. Freeman, How Children Learn (Box 6)
  - Charles W. Waddle, An Introduction to Child Psychology (Box 6)
  - May Ayres, Jesse F. Williams and Thomas D. Wood, Healthful Schools (Box 6)
  - Calvin N. Kendall and George A. Mirick, How to Teach the Special Subjects (Box 6)
  - Walter Scott Monroe, Measuring the Results of Teaching (Box 6)
  - J. B. Sears, Classroom Organization and Control (Box 6)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Rural Life and Education (Box 6)
  - Lewis M. Terman, The Hygiene of the School Child (Box 6)
  - Mabel Irene Emerson, The Evolution of the Educational Ideal (Box 6)
  - Ernest Bryant Hoag and Lewis M. Terman, Health Work in the Schools (Box 6)
  - Arthur C. Perry, Jr., Discipline as a School Problem (Box 6)
  - Calvin N. Kendall and George A. Mirick, How to Teach the Fundamental Subjects (Box 6)
  - Emma Miller Bolenius, Teaching Literature in the Grammar Grades and High School (Box 6)
  - Ellwood P. Cubberley, Public School Administration (Box 6)
  - Frank Nugent Freeman, The Psychology of Common Branches (Box 6)
  - Lewis M. Terman, The Measurement of Intelligence (Box 6)
  - Lewis M. Terman, Test Material for the Measurement of Intelligence (Box 6)
  - Frank N. Freeman, Experimental Education (Box 6)
  - David Snedden, Problems of Secondary Education (Box 6)
  - Walter Robinson Smith, An Introduction to Educational Sociology (Box 6)
  - Charles Swain Thomas, The Teaching of English (Box 6)
  - Thomas Jackson Woofter, Teaching in Rural Schools (Box 6)
  - Walter Scott Monroe, James Clarence DeVoss and Frederick James Kelly, Educational Tests and Measurements (Box 6)
  - Harold O. Rugg, Statistical Methods Applied to Education (Box 6)